<video video_id="105165259457">
    <video_creator video_creator_id="348191246181">
        <first_name>Ed</first_name>
        <last_name>Burdette</last_name>
        <email>ed.burdette@nagwa.com</email>
    </video_creator>
    <video_type>Lesson</video_type>
    <subject>Physics</subject>
    <publication_date>2020-03-04</publication_date>
    <duration>927452.00</duration>
    <language>
        <source>en</source>
    </language>
    <title>Inductance</title>
    <seo_meta_description>In this video, we will learn how to calculate the self-inductance of a conducting loop and the mutual inductance of a pair of conducting coils.</seo_meta_description>
    <transcript>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:00:00.510" end_time="00:00:02.980">In this video, we’re talking about
                inductance.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:03.270" end_time="00:00:07.600">This term refers to the way that
                current-carrying conductors resist change.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:07.760" end_time="00:00:10.900">In particular, they resist a change
                in their own current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:11.470" end_time="00:00:13.320">We’ll see how this all works in a
                bit.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:13.730" end_time="00:00:20.060">But to get started, let’s consider
                that inductance basically involves the interaction of two physical properties.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:20.270" end_time="00:00:26.620">It involves magnetic flux,
                symbolized Φ sub 𝑚, and it involves current, symbolized capital 𝐼.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:27.020" end_time="00:00:30.800">Now, we know that current is charge
                that flows through a closed circuit.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:31.080" end_time="00:00:34.210">And we can remind ourselves of what
                magnetic flux means.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:00:34.520" end_time="00:00:48.030">If we have some area, and we can
                call that area capital 𝐴, and there’s a magnetic field 𝐵 passing uniformly through
                that area, then we would say the magnetic flux through this loop of area 𝐴 is equal
                to 𝐵 times 𝐴.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:48.430" end_time="00:00:52.940">This shows us that magnetic flux is
                a magnetic field spread over some area.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:53.330" end_time="00:00:59.420">Now, it’s worth saying a quick word
                about the units of magnetic flux because this will come up in example exercises.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:59.760" end_time="00:01:10.170">Considering how magnetic flux is
                defined, we know that the SI base units of magnetic field are teslas, capital 𝑇,
                and that the base unit of area is meter squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:10.540" end_time="00:01:14.080">So magnetic flux is measured in
                teslas meter squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:14.390" end_time="00:01:17.370">And the name for that simplified
                unit is the weber.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:01:17.990" end_time="00:01:21.650">So magnetic flux is measured in
                webers, abbreviated this way.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:21.830" end_time="00:01:25.080">And each weber is equal to one
                tesla times a meter squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:25.560" end_time="00:01:34.160">Knowing this about magnetic flux,
                let’s get back to this idea that inductance is basically about these two physical
                quantities, magnetic flux and current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:34.550" end_time="00:01:40.660">Say that we have a loop of wire,
                like this, that’s carrying a current 𝐼 clockwise as we see it.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:41.210" end_time="00:01:45.960">We can remember that a
                current-carrying wire produces a magnetic field around itself.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:46.300" end_time="00:01:53.320">So in the case of our wire, this
                would produce a magnetic field that points into the screen inside this loop of
                wire.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:53.650" end_time="00:02:03.500">And if we combine the effects of
                all of these magnetic field lines, what we have is some total magnetic field, we
                could call it 𝐵, within the area of the cross section of this wire.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:03.860" end_time="00:02:07.080">In other words, we have a magnetic
                flux through this loop.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:02:07.590" end_time="00:02:18.490">Whatever this value is, if we take
                the ratio of that magnetic flux to the current 𝐼 that moves through the loop, then
                this is equal to what’s called the loop’s inductance, symbolized capital 𝐿.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:18.880" end_time="00:02:25.270">We mentioned that inductance is a
                measure of how much a current-carrying wire resists a change in its current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:25.710" end_time="00:02:32.000">So the higher 𝐿 — the inductance
                of this circuit — is, the harder it is to change the current 𝐼 running through
                it.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:32.600" end_time="00:02:43.720">Now, it may seem obvious, but when
                we talk about the inductance of this current-carrying wire, we’re talking about how
                the current in this wire responds to the magnetic flux created by that current.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:02:44.240" end_time="00:02:54.580">All that to say, when we talk about
                inductance symbolized this way, we’re really talking about the self-inductance of a
                wire, how its current responds to the flux that it creates.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:54.970" end_time="00:02:59.850">We bring all this up because
                there’s another kind of inductance, called mutual inductance.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:00.310" end_time="00:03:05.030">This has to do with more than one
                current-carrying wire, and we’ll talk about it soon.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:05.430" end_time="00:03:20.010">So far, though, we just need to
                know that the inductance of a current-carrying wire describes quantitatively how
                much it resists a change in current and that it’s equal to the ratio of the magnetic
                flux through a current-carrying loop divided by that current.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:03:20.550" end_time="00:03:25.240">Now, talking about magnetic flux
                may remind us of the law known as Faraday’s law.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:25.530" end_time="00:03:40.830">This law tells us that if we have a
                conducting loop, even if that loop has no current in it, so long as the magnetic
                flux Φ sub 𝑚 through that loop is changing in time, then, believe it or not, an
                electromotive force, an emf, will be induced in the loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:41.450" end_time="00:03:48.050">Now, as far as the rest of this
                equation goes, this capital 𝑁 refers to the number of turns in the loop or loops in
                a coil.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:48.590" end_time="00:03:53.300">And then this minus sign here just
                refers to the direction of induced current movement.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:53.730" end_time="00:04:03.470">So Faraday’s law involves a
                magnetic flux, really a change in magnetic flux, and then an induced emf, which
                creates a current in a conducting loop.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:04:03.930" end_time="00:04:08.920">So we can see some elements in
                Faraday’s law that also appear in this equation for inductance.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:09.140" end_time="00:04:16.580">And in fact, we can write an
                expression for the emf induced in a conducting loop in terms of the inductance of
                that loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:17.090" end_time="00:04:18.130">It looks like this.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:18.600" end_time="00:04:31.280">Given a conducting loop with
                inductance capital 𝐿, if we change the current in that loop over some amount of
                time, then that time rate of change times the loop’s inductance is equal to the emf
                induced in it.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:04:31.900" end_time="00:04:36.120">Knowing this, we can actually
                combine this relationship with Faraday’s law.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:36.440" end_time="00:04:40.630">And as we do, let’s say that we’re
                talking about the magnitude of the emf induced.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:40.850" end_time="00:04:43.640">So that way, we can just neglect
                this minus sign here.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:43.990" end_time="00:05:02.030">Okay, so if emf is equal to 𝐿
                times Δ𝐼 over Δ𝑡 and its magnitude is also equal to the number of turns in a coil
                multiplied by the change in magnetic flux through one of those loops divided by the
                change in time, then we can equate the right sides of those two equations.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:02.160" end_time="00:05:11.360">And notice that on both sides we
                have Δ𝑡 in the denominator, which means that if we multiply both sides by Δ𝑡, then
                that time interval cancels out.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:05:12.070" end_time="00:05:17.330">So this is another way of
                expressing inductance based on these two relationships here.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:17.800" end_time="00:05:22.410">Now, earlier, we said that
                self-inductance isn’t the only kind of inductance there is.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:22.640" end_time="00:05:28.910">Mutual inductance, and we saw an
                example of this on our opening screen, is another way for induction to happen.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:29.320" end_time="00:05:30.290">It works like this.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:30.570" end_time="00:05:36.420">Say that we have a current in a
                conducting loop such that it creates a magnetic field through that loop that looks
                this way.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:36.650" end_time="00:05:42.440">Now, say we put a second conducting
                loop in a position so that this magnetic field went through it.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:42.790" end_time="00:05:47.210">In that case, there will be a
                magnetic field moving through the cross-sectional area of this loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:47.430" end_time="00:05:49.620">And that would mean a magnetic flux
                in the loop.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:05:50.120" end_time="00:05:56.720">Faraday’s law says that a change in
                magnetic flux happening over some amount of time induces an emf.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:57.020" end_time="00:05:59.910">And that means that charge would
                start to flow in this loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:00.350" end_time="00:06:07.220">Now, the change in magnetic flux
                we’re talking about could be the initial movement of this conducting loop into the
                magnetic field.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:07.470" end_time="00:06:14.490">But of course, once the loop is
                there, assuming there’s no change in the magnetic field through it, there’d also be
                no change in magnetic flux.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:06:14.640" end_time="00:06:16.160">But what if we did this?</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:16.480" end_time="00:06:21.290">What if we gradually increased the
                magnitude of the current in this loop over here?</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:21.670" end_time="00:06:27.650">That would create an increasing
                magnetic field, which would lead to an increase in magnetic flux through this
                smaller loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:28.060" end_time="00:06:35.510">So long as current is changing
                then, in this primary loop we could call it, then it will drive the creation of
                current in this secondary loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:35.820" end_time="00:06:44.890">That induced current direction will
                be such that it creates a magnetic field which opposes the change in magnetic flux
                experienced by this current loop.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:06:45.430" end_time="00:06:48.860">This overall process is referred to
                as mutual induction.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:49.270" end_time="00:06:55.310">And rather than symbolizing this
                kind of induction with a capital 𝐿, it’s typically a capital 𝑀 that is used.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:55.560" end_time="00:07:00.530">So, for example, in this equation
                over here, instead of an 𝐿, we might see an 𝑀.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:00.770" end_time="00:07:13.550">But it would still mean essentially
                the same thing, that some inductance, whether self-inductance or mutual, multiplied
                by a change in current over a change in time is equal to the induced emf in a
                current-carrying loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:14.010" end_time="00:07:20.600">The same thing is true for this
                equation here, or sometimes instead of an 𝐿, we would see the 𝑀 of mutual
                inductance.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:07:20.840" end_time="00:07:28.590">It’s worth pointing out that rather
                than being a rare occurrence, mutual inductance is the operating principle for
                electrical transformers.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:28.940" end_time="00:07:34.030">Say we had a transformer here
                consisting of a core and a primary and secondary circuit.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:34.410" end_time="00:07:43.680">If the current in the primary
                circuit changes in time, then that will create a change in magnetic field
                transmitted by the core through the coils of the secondary circuit.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:44.080" end_time="00:07:50.550">Through mutual induction between
                these circuits, emf and then current will be induced in the secondary circuit.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:51.000" end_time="00:07:56.080">Now, whether we’re talking about
                mutual or self-inductance, the unit for inductance is the same.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:56.360" end_time="00:08:01.030">It’s the henry, named after Joseph
                Henry, and it’s abbreviated capital H.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:01.720" end_time="00:08:05.460">To understand this topic better,
                let’s now try out an example exercise.</s>
        </p>
		<question id="848163740512" media_identifier="408107030952">
          <publication_date>2020-05-02</publication_date>
          <question_title>Mutual Induction</question_title>
          <question_seo_meta_description>A transformer with an iron core has a primary coil with 25 turns and a secondary coil that also has 25 turns. The current in the primary coil increases the magnetic flux through the core by 0.15 Wb/s. The current in the secondary coil increases at 0.075 A/s. What is the mutual inductance of the coils?</question_seo_meta_description>

        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:08:05.790" end_time="00:08:12.950">A transformer with an iron core has
                a primary coil with 25 turns and a secondary coil that also has 25 turns.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:13.300" end_time="00:08:20.280">The current in the primary coil
                increases the magnetic flux through the core by 0.15 webers per second.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:20.720" end_time="00:08:26.570">The current in the secondary coil
                increases at 0.075 amperes per second.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:27.030" end_time="00:08:29.410">What is the mutual inductance of
                the coils?</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:08:29.840" end_time="00:08:34.920">To get started here, let’s draw a
                sketch of this transformer with the primary and secondary coils.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:35.320" end_time="00:08:37.660">Okay, so here’s our transformer
                core.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:37.950" end_time="00:08:40.670">And this is the primary coil; we’ll
                call this the secondary.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:40.900" end_time="00:08:47.160">And even though we can see that
                neither of these has 25 turns to it, like our problem statement tells us, we can
                pretend they do.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:47.560" end_time="00:09:01.480">The idea with the transformer is
                that as current passes through the primary coil and specifically as it changes and
                passes through this coil, then this creates a change in magnetic field that the core
                directs through the loops of the secondary coil.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:01.860" end_time="00:09:07.200">When the secondary coil experiences
                this change in magnetic flux, current is induced in it.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:07.630" end_time="00:09:11.200">In our scenario, the current in the
                primary coil is increasing.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:11.430" end_time="00:09:25.350">We don’t know the rate it’s
                increasing by, but we do know that it’s affecting the magnetic flux in the core and
                that that flux is increasing at a steady rate, given as 0.15 webers per second,
                where a weber is the unit of magnetic flux.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:25.700" end_time="00:09:35.540">Now, just as a reminder, if we have
                some area 𝐴 and there’s a magnetic field 𝐵 passing through that area, then we can
                say there’s a magnetic flux Φ sub 𝑚 through that loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:35.920" end_time="00:09:38.810">And the units of magnetic flux, as
                we’ve seen, are webers.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:39.070" end_time="00:09:48.680">So going back to our transformer,
                in the core, this iron material that connects our primary and secondary coils, the
                magnetic flux is increasing at this given rate.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:49.030" end_time="00:09:53.910">And that, our problems statement
                tells us, drives an increasing current in the secondary coil.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:54.250" end_time="00:10:01.430">We have then a change in current in
                one coil, creating a change in magnetic flux, which induces a change in current in
                another coil.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:01.690" end_time="00:10:04.550">This means we have mutual
                inductance going on.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:04.920" end_time="00:10:07.540">And we want to calculate the value
                of that inductance.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:10:07.950" end_time="00:10:10.890">To begin to do this, we can recall
                Faraday’s law.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:11.100" end_time="00:10:15.820">The reason we’re thinking of this
                law is because we have a magnetic flux that changes in time.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:16.160" end_time="00:10:29.730">Faraday’s law tells us that this
                change in flux, ΔΦ sub 𝑚, over some change in time, Δ𝑡, multiplied by the number
                of turns in whatever coil we’re considering is equal to the magnitude of the emf
                induced in that coil.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:30.110" end_time="00:10:35.000">Now, in terms of mutual inductance,
                induced emf is equal to something else as well.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:35.350" end_time="00:10:49.480">We can recall that induced emf is
                equal to the mutual inductance between two conducting loops multiplied by the time
                rate of change of current and what we can call the secondary loop or, in the example
                of our transformer, the secondary coil.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:10:49.910" end_time="00:10:52.890">So it’s 𝑀, the mutual inductance,
                that we want to solve for.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:53.140" end_time="00:11:11.140">And we see that that value
                multiplied by Δ𝐼 divided by Δ𝑡 is equal to the emf induced in a secondary coil,
                which by Faraday’s law is also equal to negative the number of turns or loops in the
                coil multiplied by the change in magnetic flux divided by the change in time.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:11.490" end_time="00:11:20.750">Since we’re given this time rate of
                change of magnetic flux, let’s combine these two equations for induced emf by
                equating the right sides with one another.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:11:21.100" end_time="00:11:27.970">When we do this though, we’ll leave
                off this minus sign here because in our case we’re only concerned with the magnitude
                of the emf induced.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:28.260" end_time="00:11:29.700">So then we get this.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:29.870" end_time="00:11:46.370">𝑀, the mutual inductance of the
                coils, times Δ𝐼 divided by Δ𝑡, the time rate of change of current in the secondary
                coil, is equal to the number of loops in that coil multiplied by the time rate of
                change of magnetic flux that each loop in the coil experiences.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:11:46.610" end_time="00:11:51.060">What we want to do is isolate 𝑀
                since we’re solving for the mutual inductance.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:51.230" end_time="00:11:55.710">And to do that, we’ll divide both
                sides of the equation by Δ𝐼 divided by Δ𝑡.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:55.960" end_time="00:12:14.930">When we do, on the right-hand side
                of the resulting equation, we have 𝑁 — the number of turns in the secondary coil,
                that’s 25 — multiplied by the time rate of change of magnetic flux in the core,
                that’s given as 0.15 webers per second, divided by the time rate of change of
                current in the secondary coil.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:15.190" end_time="00:12:20.590">This is the induced current, and
                its rate of change is 0.075 amperes per second.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:20.980" end_time="00:12:27.030">When we calculate this fraction and
                keep two significant figures, we find a result of 50 henrys.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:27.380" end_time="00:12:29.970">That’s the mutual inductance of the
                two coils.</s>
        </p>
		</question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:12:30.690" end_time="00:12:33.180">Let’s look now at a second example
                exercise.</s>
        </p>
		<question id="472174025780" media_identifier="592161038072">
          <publication_date>2020-05-02</publication_date>
          <question_title>Self-Induction</question_title>
          <question_seo_meta_description>A loop of wire carries a current of 180 mA. The magnetic flux produced by the current is 0.77 Wb. What is the self-inductance of the loop?</question_seo_meta_description>

        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:12:33.520" end_time="00:12:37.290">A loop of wire carries a current of
                180 milliamperes.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:37.580" end_time="00:12:41.790">The magnetic flux produced by the
                current is 0.77 webers.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:42.110" end_time="00:12:44.150">What is the self-inductance of the
                loop?</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:12:44.620" end_time="00:12:47.180">So then, in this example, we have a
                loop of wire.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:47.320" end_time="00:12:48.240">Let’s say this is it.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:48.430" end_time="00:12:51.740">And it’s carrying a current of 180
                milliamperes.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:51.880" end_time="00:12:55.610">Because of this, a magnetic field
                is produced that passes through the loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:55.980" end_time="00:12:58.490">Let’s just say the magnetic field
                points like this.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:58.700" end_time="00:13:05.460">And because we have this field
                passing through the interior area of the loop, that means we have a magnetic flux
                through the loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:05.850" end_time="00:13:10.890">And that’s the value we have given
                to us here in our problem statement, 0.77 webers.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:11.230" end_time="00:13:14.860">We can refer to that symbolically
                as Φ sub 𝑚, magnetic flux.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:13:15.220" end_time="00:13:18.700">Knowing all this, we want to solve
                for the self-inductance of the loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:18.950" end_time="00:13:29.780">And we can recall that the
                self-inductance of a loop, capital 𝐿, is equal to the ratio of the magnetic flux Φ
                sub 𝑚 produced by a current 𝐼 in the loop to that current 𝐼.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:30.180" end_time="00:13:33.670">For our particular loop then, we
                have exactly that information about it.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:34.060" end_time="00:13:36.150">Our current 𝐼 is a current in the
                loop.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:36.490" end_time="00:13:41.210">And the magnetic flux is produced
                thanks to a magnetic field generated by that current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:41.660" end_time="00:13:46.600">So to solve for the self-inductance
                of our loop, we only need to divide Φ sub 𝑚 by 𝐼.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:13:46.980" end_time="00:13:54.810">With these values plugged in, the
                one change we’ll want to make before dividing is to convert the units of our current
                from milliamperes to amperes.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:55.130" end_time="00:14:03.570">Now, since 1000 milliamperes is
                equal to one amp, we can say that 180 milliamperes is equal to 0.180 amps.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:04.020" end_time="00:14:05.390">And now we’re ready to divide.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:05.760" end_time="00:14:10.440">And when we do, to two significant
                figures, we find a result of 4.3 henrys.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:10.760" end_time="00:14:12.870">That’s the self-inductance of this
                loop.</s>
        </p>
		</question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:14:14.060" end_time="00:14:17.230">Let’s summarize now what we’ve
                learned in this lesson on inductance.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:17.660" end_time="00:14:23.600">Earlier on, we saw that inductance
                is the tendency of a current-carrying conductor to resist a change in current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:24.060" end_time="00:14:33.700">The inductance of a circuit,
                sometimes called its self-inductance, is equal to the ratio of the magnetic flux
                through the current loop divided by that current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:34.170" end_time="00:14:50.240">We also learned that Faraday’s law
                led us to another relationship describing inductance, that the inductance in a
                circuit multiplied by the time rate of change of current in that circuit is equal to
                the number of loops or turns in the circuit times the time rate of change of
                magnetic flux.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:14:50.660" end_time="00:15:08.100">We learned further about mutual
                inductance, symbolized using a capital 𝑀, which occurs when a change in current, in
                what we could call a primary coil, creates a change in magnetic field, which is then
                experienced by a secondary coil where that change in flux through the secondary coil
                induces a current.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:08.560" end_time="00:15:24.580">This, we saw, is the basic
                principle behind electrical transformers and can be described by saying that the
                mutual inductance between two coils or two loops of wire multiplied by the time rate
                of change of current in the secondary wire is equal to the emf induced there.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:25.060" end_time="00:15:27.030">This is a summary of
                inductance.</s>
        </p>
    </transcript>
</video>
