<video video_id="106179801401">
    <video_creator video_creator_id="978107247356">
        <first_name>Anita</first_name>
        <last_name>Piatek</last_name>
        <email>anita.piatek@nagwa.com</email>
    </video_creator>
    <video_type>Lesson</video_type>
    <subject>Mathematics</subject>
    <publication_date>2020-05-18</publication_date>
    <duration>1005146.00</duration>
    <language>
        <source>en</source>
    </language>
    <title>Finding the 𝑛th Term of a Geometric Sequence</title>
    <seo_meta_description>In this video, we will learn how to write explicit and recursive formulas for geometric sequences, to find the value of the nth term in a geometric sequence, and to find a term’s order given its value.</seo_meta_description>
    <transcript>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:00:02.210" end_time="00:00:05.410">In this video, we will learn about
                geometric sequences.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:05.740" end_time="00:00:11.270">We will discover how to find the
                general or 𝑛th term and how to find the term-to-term rule.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:11.480" end_time="00:00:15.650">We’ll also cover how to find the
                order of a term given its value.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:00:16.550" end_time="00:00:23.560">The first thing to note about a
                geometric sequence is these are sequences where the ratio between terms is
                constant.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:23.870" end_time="00:00:29.920">Notice that that’s different to
                arithmetic sequences, where it’s the difference between terms that’s constant.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:30.400" end_time="00:00:38.860">We can describe a geometric
                sequence in one of two ways, either by using a term-to-term rule or by using a
                position-to-term rule.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:39.270" end_time="00:00:46.290">The position-to-term rule is often
                called the 𝑛th term, and it’s very helpful for finding the value of a specific
                term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:46.550" end_time="00:01:01.890">For example, if we wanted to find
                the 15th term of a sequence, we could directly evaluate it by substituting 15 into
                the 𝑛th term rule rather than having to work out all the terms up to the 15th one
                using the term-to-term rule.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:01:02.560" end_time="00:01:06.870">So, let’s think about some of the
                notation that we use in geometric sequences.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:07.180" end_time="00:01:15.910">We say that if the first term is
                denoted as the letter 𝑎 and the common ratio is 𝑟, then our sequence would look
                like this.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:17.150" end_time="00:01:18.920">The first term is 𝑎.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:19.340" end_time="00:01:25.710">The second term would be 𝑎𝑟
                because we’ve multiplied the first term 𝑎 by the common ratio 𝑟.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:25.950" end_time="00:01:31.170">Multiplying the second term 𝑎𝑟
                with another 𝑟 would give us 𝑎𝑟 squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:31.590" end_time="00:01:34.880">We can signify the terms by using
                subscript notation.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:35.110" end_time="00:01:44.360">For example, the first term would
                be written as 𝑎 sub one, the second term would be written as 𝑎 sub two, the third
                as 𝑎 sub three, and so on.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:01:44.870" end_time="00:01:50.710">So, how could we find a rule to
                find the 𝑛th term which is written as 𝑎 sub 𝑛?</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:51.230" end_time="00:01:58.590">Well, we could start by noticing
                that each term has an exponent value of 𝑟 which is one less than the term
                number.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:01:58.930" end_time="00:02:06.330">We know that the 𝑛th term would
                still have an 𝑎-value, and the exponent of 𝑟 would be one less than 𝑛.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:06.870" end_time="00:02:15.180">We can, therefore, say that the
                𝑛th term of any geometric sequence can be written as 𝑎 times 𝑟 to the power of 𝑛
                minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:15.560" end_time="00:02:22.760">We remember, of course, that it’s
                just the 𝑟 that’s taken to the power of 𝑛 minus one and it doesn’t include the 𝑎
                as well.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:23.430" end_time="00:02:30.690">So, let’s see how we can put this
                formula into practice to find the 𝑛th term of our first geometric sequence.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="175127380280" media_identifier="263101659560">
            <publication_date>2020-06-24</publication_date>
            <question_title>Finding the General Term of a Given Geometric Sequence</question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>Find the general term of the geometric sequence −76,  −38,  −19, −19/2, ...</question_seo_meta_description>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:02:33.050" end_time="00:02:42.450">Find the general term of the
                geometric sequence negative 76, negative 38, negative 19, negative 19 over two.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:02:43.280" end_time="00:02:47.430">Another way of phrasing general
                term is the 𝑛th term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:47.680" end_time="00:02:55.220">So, we’re looking for the 𝑛th term
                of this geometric sequence, which is a sequence which has a common ratio between the
                terms.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:55.710" end_time="00:02:59.310">So, let’s have a look at the
                sequence and see what we can determine.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:02:59.560" end_time="00:03:04.280">Firstly, we can see the first term
                in the sequence is negative 76.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:04.570" end_time="00:03:11.360">When we’re working with geometric
                sequences, we usually use the letter 𝑎 to signify the first term of the
                sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:11.880" end_time="00:03:17.120">In order to find the 𝑛th term,
                we’ll also need to find 𝑟, the common ratio.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:17.580" end_time="00:03:31.400">When we consider a general
                geometric sequence written as 𝑎 then 𝑎𝑟 then 𝑎𝑟 squared, and so on, we can find
                the common ratio 𝑟 by dividing any term by the immediately preceding term.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:03:31.750" end_time="00:03:37.910">So, here, we could take the second
                term of negative 38 and divide it by negative 76.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:38.170" end_time="00:03:40.900">Therefore, 𝑟 is equal to
                one-half.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:41.150" end_time="00:03:54.280">Notice that even if we’d taken two
                different terms, for example, if we divided the third term of negative 19 by the
                second term of negative 38, we would still have found the common ratio 𝑟 to be
                one-half.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:03:54.680" end_time="00:03:59.130">After all, if it wasn’t the same,
                then we wouldn’t have a geometric sequence.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:03:59.480" end_time="00:04:06.870">So now that we found the values of
                𝑎 and 𝑟, we recall the general formula for the nth term of a geometric
                sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:07.430" end_time="00:04:14.240">𝑎 sub 𝑛, that’s the 𝑛th term, is
                equal to 𝑎 times 𝑟 to the power of 𝑛 minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:14.610" end_time="00:04:22.240">All we need to do now is plug in
                the values of 𝑎 equals negative six and 𝑟 equals a half into this formula.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:22.700" end_time="00:04:29.720">This gives us 𝑎 sub 𝑛 equals
                negative 76 times a half to the power of 𝑛 minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:04:30.180" end_time="00:04:37.380">As we can’t simplify this any
                further, then that’s our answer for the general term or the 𝑛th term of the
                geometric sequence.</s>
        </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:04:39.300" end_time="00:04:45.120">Let’s have a look at another
                question where we’re finding the 𝑛th term of a slightly more complex sequence.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="648135917479" media_identifier="532180375847" >
            <publication_date>2020-06-24</publication_date>
            <question_seo_meta_description>Find, in terms of 𝑛, the general term of the sequence (1/4, 9/16, 81/64, 729/256, ...)</question_seo_meta_description>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:04:47.650" end_time="00:05:00.540">Find, in terms of 𝑛, the general
                term of the sequence one-fourth, nine over 16, 81 over 64, 729 over 256, and so
                on.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:05:01.590" end_time="00:05:05.260">In this question, we’re given the
                first four terms of this sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:05.670" end_time="00:05:12.810">There doesn’t look like there’s a
                common difference between the terms, so we could say that this is definitely not an
                arithmetic sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:13.300" end_time="00:05:22.420">We can check if it’s a geometric
                sequence which would have a common ratio between the terms by seeing if we can work
                out what that common ratio would be.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:05:23.020" end_time="00:05:34.340">In order to find the ratio 𝑟
                between the first two terms, we would take the second term, nine over 16, and divide
                by the term before it, one-quarter.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:34.610" end_time="00:05:42.620">We can recall that to divide by
                one-quarter, that would be equivalent to multiplying by the reciprocal, which would
                be four over one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:42.920" end_time="00:05:48.840">We can simplify the four on the
                numerator and the 16 on the denominator by taking out a factor of four.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:49.070" end_time="00:05:51.920">We then multiply our numerators and
                denominators.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:52.160" end_time="00:05:56.250">Nine times one would give us nine,
                and four times one gives us four.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:05:56.660" end_time="00:06:01.410">We can check if there’s the same
                ratio between the third term and the second term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:01.700" end_time="00:06:06.360">So, we calculate 81 over 64 divided
                by nine over 16.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:06.760" end_time="00:06:11.460">We can see that the reciprocal of
                nine over 16 would be 16 over nine.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:11.800" end_time="00:06:20.770">And we simplify the fractions
                before multiplying the numerators and denominators, which gives us the same common
                ratio 𝑟 of nine over four.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:21.010" end_time="00:06:35.640">And if we check this by working out
                what we need to multiply the third term 81 over 64 by in order to get the fourth
                term of 729 over 256, we get the same answer of nine over four.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:06:36.350" end_time="00:06:40.650">So, let’s think about how we would
                find the general term of this sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:40.920" end_time="00:06:45.620">We can recall that the general term
                is another way of saying the 𝑛th term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:46.010" end_time="00:06:54.800">We can recall that the formula to
                find the 𝑛th term 𝑎 sub 𝑛 is that 𝑎 sub 𝑛 is equal to 𝑎 times 𝑟 to the power
                of 𝑛 minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:55.090" end_time="00:07:01.550">The 𝑟-value represents the common
                ratio, and the 𝑎-value represents the first term of the sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:01.900" end_time="00:07:09.680">We’ve already established that 𝑟
                is equal to nine over four, and the 𝑎-value, the first term in the sequence, would
                be one-quarter.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:10.050" end_time="00:07:14.530">We can then take the values of 𝑎
                and 𝑟 and plug them into this formula.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:14.850" end_time="00:07:21.350">This gives us 𝑎 sub 𝑛 equals
                one-quarter times nine-quarters to the power of 𝑛 minus one.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:07:21.770" end_time="00:07:30.810">While this is a perfectly valid
                answer for the 𝑛th term of the sequence, it might be worth seeing if we can
                simplify this right-hand side any further.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:31.100" end_time="00:07:37.130">We can start our simplification by
                thinking about what happens when we have a power of a fraction.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:37.600" end_time="00:07:45.580">A fraction with a certain exponent
                value is equivalent to the numerator with that exponent over the denominator with
                that exponent.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:45.910" end_time="00:07:58.570">If we then consider these fractions
                multiplied, multiplying the numerators one times nine to the power of 𝑛 minus one
                would give us the value on the numerator of nine to the power of 𝑛 minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:58.910" end_time="00:08:04.760">Multiplying the denominators would
                give us four times four to the power of 𝑛 minus one.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:08:05.230" end_time="00:08:16.020">If we look at the denominator, we
                can apply another exponent rule that 𝑥 to the power of 𝑎 multiplied by 𝑥 to the
                power of 𝑏 is equal to 𝑥 to the power of 𝑎 plus 𝑏.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:16.380" end_time="00:08:20.000">On the denominator, the 𝑥-value
                here would be four.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:20.150" end_time="00:08:26.740">And our 𝑎- and 𝑏-values, that’s
                the exponents, would be represented by one and 𝑛 minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:27.140" end_time="00:08:31.590">Adding one and 𝑛 minus one would
                leave us with the value of 𝑛.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:31.960" end_time="00:08:38.130">So, we’ve found a fully simplified
                answer for the general term of this sequence in terms of 𝑛.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:38.330" end_time="00:08:43.140">It’s nine to the power of 𝑛 minus
                one over four to the power of 𝑛.</s>
        </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:08:45.140" end_time="00:08:51.100">In the two questions that we’ve
                just seen, we’ve been finding the 𝑛th term or the position-to-term rule.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:51.390" end_time="00:08:56.440">In the next question, we’ll have a
                look at how we would find a term-to-term rule.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="" media_identifier="" pause_reason="no_live_question">
            <publication_date></publication_date>
            <question_title></question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>Find a recursive formula for the sequence 486, 162, 54, 18, 6, 2, 2/3.</question_seo_meta_description>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:08:59.290" end_time="00:09:10.480">Find a recursive formula for the
                sequence 486, 162, 54, 18, six, two, two-thirds.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:11.400" end_time="00:09:19.370">So here we have a sequence which
                begins with the number 486, and we’re asked to find a recursive formula.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:19.630" end_time="00:09:27.310">This means that instead of finding
                a general term or an 𝑛th term for the sequence, we’re going to find a term-to-term
                rule.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:27.610" end_time="00:09:32.370">It means we’ll be thinking about
                how we go from one term to another term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:32.830" end_time="00:09:37.210">Let’s begin by seeing if we can
                find a common ratio between the terms.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:37.380" end_time="00:09:40.140">We can signify this with the letter
                𝑟.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:40.760" end_time="00:09:55.530">In a geometric sequence, we say
                that the first term is 𝑎, the second term would be 𝑎 times the common ratio 𝑟,
                the third term would be 𝑎𝑟 squared, and the fourth term would be 𝑎𝑟 cubed, and
                so on.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:55.940" end_time="00:10:02.710">Therefore, to find the ratio
                between terms, we take any term and divide by the term immediately before it.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:10:03.090" end_time="00:10:10.440">So, we could, for example, take the
                second term of 162 and divide by the term before it, 486.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:10.740" end_time="00:10:16.790">Or if it’s a geometric sequence, as
                we assume, then we could take the third term and divide by the second term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:17.100" end_time="00:10:21.400">We could even take the sixth term
                of two and divide by the fifth term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:21.800" end_time="00:10:26.930">We should hopefully see
                straightaway that two-sixths can simplify to one-third.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:27.250" end_time="00:10:31.340">So, do the other two fractions here
                also simplify to one-third?</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:31.720" end_time="00:10:35.840">Well, if we take 54 and add 54,
                that’s 108.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:36.070" end_time="00:10:39.970">And adding another 54 would give us
                162.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:40.250" end_time="00:10:43.410">So, this fraction would also
                simplify to one-third.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:43.890" end_time="00:10:49.380">162 over 486 would also give us
                one-third.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:10:49.970" end_time="00:10:53.340">It’s looking like we have a common
                ratio of one-third.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:53.620" end_time="00:11:02.390">In fact, if we take any two
                consecutive terms in this sequence, we find that we need to multiply the first one
                by one-third to get the second.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:02.800" end_time="00:11:08.000">The terms we have been given
                definitely do have a common ratio of one-third.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:08.720" end_time="00:11:12.730">So, does this answer the question
                then to find a recursive formula?</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:13.020" end_time="00:11:18.730">Is it sufficient to say we would
                multiply a term by one-third to find the next one?</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:11:19.130" end_time="00:11:20.400">Well, not quite.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:20.980" end_time="00:11:23.510">We can use some more formal
                notation here.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:24.040" end_time="00:11:29.350">We say that the first term 𝑎 one
                will be equal to 486.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:29.890" end_time="00:11:36.680">To find the second term, we know
                that that would be 486 times the ratio 𝑟 of one-third.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:37.050" end_time="00:11:42.140">So, 𝑎 sub two, the second term, is
                equal to one-third of 𝑎 sub one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:42.600" end_time="00:11:51.970">In the same way, if we wanted to
                find the third term and we didn’t know the value of it, we take the second term and
                multiply it by the ratio 𝑟 of one-third.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:52.390" end_time="00:11:59.460">We could continue like this to say
                the fourth term would be equal to one-third times the third term.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:11:59.920" end_time="00:12:10.790">So, if we wanted to find the 𝑛th
                term of this sequence, we would calculate one-third multiplied by the term before,
                written as 𝑎 sub 𝑛 minus one.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:11.380" end_time="00:12:21.700">This is where we get the helpful
                formula from, that if we want to find the 𝑛 plus oneth term of a sequence, then we
                multiply the common ratio by the 𝑛th term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:22.400" end_time="00:12:32.600">It sort of looks like the formula
                for the 𝑛th term of a sequence, but this time the term is based on the term before
                it rather than the starting term of a sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:33.250" end_time="00:12:43.530">But here, we can give our answer
                that any term in the sequence 𝑎 sub 𝑛 can be calculated by a third times the term
                before it, 𝑎 sub 𝑛 minus one.</s>
        </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:12:45.580" end_time="00:12:52.740">In the next question, we’ll see how
                we can find the order of a term given its value and the 𝑛th term of the
                sequence.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="467198792769" media_identifier="385127940739">
            <publication_date>2020-06-24</publication_date>
            <question_title>Finding the Order of a Term in a Geometric Sequence given Its Value and General Term</question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>Find the order of the term whose value is 4,374 in the geometric sequence 𝑎_𝑛 = (2/3)(3)^𝑛.</question_seo_meta_description>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:12:55.480" end_time="00:13:06.750">Find the order of the term whose
                value is 4374 in the geometric sequence 𝑎 sub 𝑛 equals two-thirds times three to
                the power of 𝑛.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:13:08.000" end_time="00:13:11.000">Let’s start by looking at the
                information that we’re given.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:11.370" end_time="00:13:16.190">This value of 𝑎 sub 𝑛 represents
                the 𝑛th term of this sequence.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:16.610" end_time="00:13:22.560">We’re asked to find the order of
                the term whose value is 4374.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:22.870" end_time="00:13:29.550">That means that we’ve got a
                sequence, and somewhere in this sequence is this value of 4374.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:29.930" end_time="00:13:36.880">The order of this term means we’re
                really asking, is it the second term, the 10th term, the 100th term?</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:37.220" end_time="00:13:38.700">That’s what we need to find
                out.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:39.250" end_time="00:13:48.420">We can do this by saying let’s make
                the order of this term 𝑛, and then our 𝑛th term will be 4374.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:48.950" end_time="00:13:56.790">We could then fill this into the
                formula and rearrange to find this value of 𝑛, which would give us the order of
                this term.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:13:57.380" end_time="00:14:02.730">We can start our rearranging by
                dividing both sides of this equation by two-thirds.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:03.140" end_time="00:14:09.570">On the left-hand side, we can
                recall that to divide by a fraction, we multiply by its reciprocal.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:09.950" end_time="00:14:14.030">And on the right-hand side, we’ll
                be left with three to the power of 𝑛.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:14.480" end_time="00:14:17.220">We can simplify the values on the
                left-hand side.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:17.480" end_time="00:14:28.150">So, we work out 2187 multiplied by
                three, which gives us 6561 is equal to three to the power of 𝑛.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:14:28.640" end_time="00:14:35.060">Now, at this stage, there’s a
                branch of mathematics called logarithms, which would help us solve this problem
                directly.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:35.380" end_time="00:14:43.420">But as most people learn this long
                after they learn about geometric sequences, we’ll use a bit of trial and improvement
                here instead.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:44.080" end_time="00:14:54.090">Remember that a value like three to
                the power of 𝑛 equals 6561 is really equivalent to saying three to the power of
                what gives us this value.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:54.570" end_time="00:15:01.740">You might know your first powers of
                three off by heart, up to roughly three to the power of four equals 81.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:02.080" end_time="00:15:07.850">We could then continue with a few
                more by multiplying each of the values by three as we go up.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:08.130" end_time="00:15:13.850">If we’re using a non-calculator
                method, we’ll probably need to start using some pencil and paper working out.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:14.280" end_time="00:15:20.760">But then, we find that three to the
                power of eight is equal to 6561.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:21.110" end_time="00:15:25.440">This means that our 𝑛-value here
                must be equal to eight.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:26.020" end_time="00:15:35.590">So, we can give our answer that the
                order of the term whose value is 4374 is eight, as it would be the eighth term in
                this sequence.</s>
        </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:15:37.750" end_time="00:15:40.710">We can now summarize what we’ve
                learnt in this video.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:41.660" end_time="00:15:48.090">Firstly, we saw that a geometric
                sequence is a sequence where the ratio between terms is constant.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:48.660" end_time="00:15:59.880">For a first term 𝑎 and a common
                ratio 𝑟, we have the terms of the sequence as 𝑎, 𝑎𝑟, 𝑎𝑟 squared, 𝑎𝑟 to the
                third power, and so on.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:16:00.670" end_time="00:16:08.040">To find the common ratio 𝑟 given a
                value of terms in a sequence, we can divide any term by its preceding term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:16:08.340" end_time="00:16:12.840">For example, 𝑟 can be found by
                dividing the third term by the second term.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:16:13.500" end_time="00:16:22.200">The position-to-term rule or the
                𝑛th term can be written as 𝑎 sub 𝑛 equals 𝑎 times 𝑟 to the power of 𝑛 minus
                one.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:16:22.720" end_time="00:16:42.960">Finally, we saw the term-to-term
                rule, or recursive formula, which can be written as 𝑎 sub 𝑛 plus one equals 𝑟
                times 𝑎 sub 𝑛, remembering that this means if we want to find the value of the
                term with order 𝑛 plus one, then we take the value of the term with order 𝑛 and
                multiply it by the common ratio 𝑟.</s>
        </p>
    </transcript>
</video>
