<video video_id="106196394262">
    <video_creator video_creator_id="580178428347">
        <first_name>Rhodri</first_name>
        <last_name>Jones</last_name>
        <email>rhodri.jones@nagwa.com</email>
    </video_creator>
    <video_type>Lesson</video_type>
    <subject>Mathematics</subject>
    <publication_date>2019-12-31</publication_date>
    <duration>914141.00</duration>
    <language>
        <source>en</source>
    </language>
    <title>Areas of Circular Segments</title>
    <seo_meta_description>In this video, we will learn how to find the area of a circular segment.</seo_meta_description>
    <transcript>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:00:01.870" end_time="00:00:06.570">In this video, we will learn how to
                find the area of a circular segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:07.590" end_time="00:00:11.600">We will begin by looking at the
                definition of a circular segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:00:12.620" end_time="00:00:21.500">We will then identify formulas that
                can be used to calculate the area of a circular segment and then use these to solve
                some problems.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="603176259486" media_identifier="785109671394">
            <publication_date>2020-01-22</publication_date>
            <question_title>The Definition of a Circular Segment</question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>What is the definition of a circular segment? [A] A region of a circle bounded by an arc and a chord passing through the end points of the arc. [B] A region of a circle bounded by two radii and an arc. [C] A region of a circle bounded by a chord and a central angle subtended by that arc. [D] A region of a circle bounded between two chords and two arcs. [E] An arc which is half of the  circumference.</question_seo_meta_description>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:00:23.580" end_time="00:00:26.910">What is the definition of a
                    circular segment?</s>
                <s start_time ="00:00:28.440" end_time="00:00:35.560">Is it (A) a region of a circle
                    bounded by an arc and a chord passing through the end points of the arc?</s>
                <s start_time ="00:00:36.430" end_time="00:00:41.140">(B) A region of a circle
                    bounded by two radii and an arc.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:00:42.210" end_time="00:00:49.230">(C) A region of a circle
                    bounded by a chord and a central angle subtended by that arc.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:00:50.470" end_time="00:00:55.560">(D) A region of a circle
                    bounded between two chords and two arcs.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:00:55.980" end_time="00:01:00.000">Or (E) an arc which is half of
                    the circumference.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:01:01.200" end_time="00:01:05.150">The circle shown has been split
                    into two segments.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:06.300" end_time="00:01:10.140">The smaller part of the circle
                    is known as the minor segment.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:11.340" end_time="00:01:14.670">The larger part is known as the
                    major segment.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:16.210" end_time="00:01:19.600">Both of these segments are
                    bounded by an arc.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:20.860" end_time="00:01:23.600">They are also bounded by a
                    common chord.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:24.860" end_time="00:01:28.340">This means that the correct
                    definition is option (A).</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:29.720" end_time="00:01:38.440">A circular segment is a region
                    of a circle bounded by an arc and a chord passing through the end points of the
                    arc.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:01:39.690" end_time="00:01:45.820">In our diagram, we have a minor
                    segment in orange and a major segment in pink.</s>
            </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:01:48.400" end_time="00:01:54.050">We will now look at the formulas
                that can be used to calculate the area of a segment.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="284152170652" media_identifier="">
            <publication_date>2020-01-22</publication_date>
            <question_title>Identifying the Area of a Circular Segment given Its Radius and Central Angle</question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>Which formula can be used to find the area of a circular segment, given radius 𝑟 and a central angle 𝜃?</question_seo_meta_description>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:01:57.160" end_time="00:02:06.180">Which formula can be used to
                    find the area of a circular segment, given radius 𝑟 and a central angle 𝜃?</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:02:08.050" end_time="00:02:14.360">We recall that any circle can
                    be split into a minor and major segment as shown.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:02:16.050" end_time="00:02:22.020">We’re also told that the radius
                    of the circle is 𝑟 and the central angle is 𝜃.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:02:23.810" end_time="00:02:40.320">If we label the two points at
                    the end of the chord 𝐴𝐵 and the center of the circle 𝑂, then the area of the
                    segment will be equal to the area of the sector 𝐴𝑂𝐵 minus the area of
                    triangle 𝐴𝑂𝐵.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:02:41.770" end_time="00:02:48.460">It is important to note at this
                    point that our angle 𝜃 might be given in degrees or in radians.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:02:49.500" end_time="00:02:53.220">180 degrees is equal to 𝜋
                    radians.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:02:53.660" end_time="00:03:02.450">We know that a circle has a
                    total of 360 degrees, which means it will have a total of two 𝜋 radians.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:03:03.830" end_time="00:03:15.580">As a result, the area of a
                    circular segment can be calculated using two linked formulas, one for degrees
                    and one when the angle is in radians.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:03:17.150" end_time="00:03:27.010">When our angle was measured in
                    degrees, the area of a sector is equal to 𝜃 out of 360 multiplied by 𝜋𝑟
                    squared.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:03:28.370" end_time="00:03:34.050">As already mentioned, 360
                    degrees is equal to two 𝜋 radians.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:03:34.820" end_time="00:03:43.730">This means that the area of a
                    sector when 𝜃 is in radians is 𝜃 over two 𝜋 multiplied by 𝜋𝑟 squared.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:03:44.830" end_time="00:03:47.070">In this case, the 𝜋s
                    cancel.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:03:48.070" end_time="00:03:56.790">We are left with 𝜃 over two
                    multiplied by 𝑟 squared, which is often written as a half 𝑟 squared 𝜃.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:03:58.790" end_time="00:04:07.400">As we’ve worked out a formula
                    for the area of a sector in degrees and radians, we will now look at the area of
                    a triangle.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:04:08.450" end_time="00:04:16.960">The area of any triangle can be
                    calculated using the formula a half of 𝑎𝑏 multiplied by sin 𝐶.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:04:18.560" end_time="00:04:24.920">In our diagram, we can see that
                    the lengths 𝑎 and 𝑏 are both equal to the radius or 𝑟.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:04:25.420" end_time="00:04:27.980">The angle 𝐶 is equal to
                    𝜃.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:04:28.600" end_time="00:04:38.750">Therefore, the area of a
                    triangle inside a circle can be calculated using the formula half 𝑟 squared
                    multiplied by sin 𝜃.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:04:39.800" end_time="00:04:47.080">We will now clear some space to
                    work out the formula that can be used to find the area of a circular
                    segment.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:04:48.520" end_time="00:04:52.900">Let’s consider when 𝜃 is
                    measured in radians first.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:04:53.890" end_time="00:05:02.510">The area of the sector is a
                    half 𝑟 squared 𝜃, and the area of the triangle is a half 𝑟 squared sin
                    𝜃.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:05:03.920" end_time="00:05:09.320">We can factor out a half 𝑟
                    squared as this is common in both terms.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:05:10.360" end_time="00:05:16.180">Inside the parentheses or
                    bracket, we’re left with 𝜃 minus sin 𝜃.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:05:17.810" end_time="00:05:30.570">When the central angle 𝜃 is
                    given in radians, then the area of the circular segment can be calculated by
                    multiplying a half 𝑟 squared by 𝜃 minus sin 𝜃.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:05:33.040" end_time="00:05:47.310">If the central angle is given
                    in degrees, then our formula is equal to 𝜃 over 360 multiplied by 𝜋𝑟 squared
                    minus a half 𝑟 squared sin 𝜃.</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s start_time ="00:05:48.530" end_time="00:06:00.160">Whilst the 𝑟 squared is common
                    in both terms, we tend not to factor it out here but instead calculate the area
                    of the sector and area of triangle separately.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:06:01.160" end_time="00:06:06.660">We then subtract our two
                    answers to calculate the area of the circular segment.</s>
                <s start_time ="00:06:08.860" end_time="00:06:13.870">Either one of these formulas
                    can be used depending on the context of the question.</s>
            </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:06:15.160" end_time="00:06:21.420">We will now use these to find the
                area of a segment given different properties of a circle.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="763181762193" >
            <publication_date>2020-01-22</publication_date>
            <question_title>Finding the Area of a Segment given the Area of the Circle and the Segment's Central Angle</question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>The area of a circle is 227 cm² and the central angle of a segment is 120°. Find the area of the segment giving the answer to two decimal places.</question_seo_meta_description>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:06:24.600" end_time="00:06:34.360">The area of a circle is 227 square
                centimeters and the central angle of a segment is 120 degrees.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:35.300" end_time="00:06:41.010">Find the area of the segment,
                giving the answer to two decimal places.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:06:43.070" end_time="00:06:48.900">We’re told in the question that the
                central angle of a segment is 120 degrees.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:49.180" end_time="00:06:52.770">And we need to calculate the area
                of this segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:06:54.890" end_time="00:07:06.020">When the angle of a segment is
                given in degrees, we can calculate the angle of this segment by subtracting the area
                of the triangle from the area of the sector.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:07.430" end_time="00:07:14.310">The area of the sector is equal to
                𝜃 over 360 multiplied by 𝜋𝑟 squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:15.520" end_time="00:07:21.170">The area of the triangle is equal
                to a half 𝑟 squared multiplied by sin 𝜃.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:23.020" end_time="00:07:29.940">We are told in the question that
                the area of the circle is equal to 227 square centimeters.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:31.040" end_time="00:07:35.260">This means that 𝜋𝑟 squared equals
                227.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:36.600" end_time="00:07:44.170">Dividing both sides of this
                equation by 𝜋 gives us 𝑟 squared is equal to 227 over 𝜋.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:07:46.000" end_time="00:07:49.920">We can now substitute these into
                both of our formulas.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:07:51.500" end_time="00:07:59.490">The area of the sector is equal to
                120 over 360 multiplied by 227.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:00.670" end_time="00:08:09.950">This can be simplified to one-third
                multiplied by 227 or 227 over three.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:11.640" end_time="00:08:22.000">The area of the triangle can be
                calculated by multiplying a half by 227 over 𝜋 by sin of 120 degrees.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:23.170" end_time="00:08:27.820">Sin of 120 degrees is equal to root
                three over two.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:29.060" end_time="00:08:43.160">The area of the segment can
                therefore be calculated by subtracting a half multiplied by 227 over 𝜋 multiplied
                by root three over two from 227 over three.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:44.860" end_time="00:08:52.240">Typing this into the calculator
                gives us 44.37875 and so on.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:08:53.730" end_time="00:08:59.880">As we need to round our answer to
                two decimal places, the key or deciding number is the eight.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:01.140" end_time="00:09:05.210">This means that we round up to
                44.38.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:06.360" end_time="00:09:12.180">The area of the segment is 44.38
                square centimeters.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:14.590" end_time="00:09:25.960">As this is the area of the minor
                segment, we could calculate the area of the major segment by subtracting this answer
                from 227 square centimeters.</s>
        </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:29.030" end_time="00:09:33.790">We will now look at another
                question where we are given the radius and the chord.</s>
        </p>
        <question id="130175278563" media_identifier="329193812910">
            <publication_date>2020-01-22</publication_date>
            <question_title>Finding the Area of a Circular Segment</question_title>
            <question_seo_meta_description>A circle has a radius of 10 cm. A chord of length 14 cm is drawn. Find the area of the major segment, giving the answer to the nearest square centimeter.</question_seo_meta_description>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:36.610" end_time="00:09:40.130">A circle has a radius of 10
                centimeters.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:40.710" end_time="00:09:44.060">A chord of length 14 centimeters is
                drawn.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:45.050" end_time="00:09:51.330">Find the area of the major segment,
                giving the answer to the nearest square centimeter.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:09:53.400" end_time="00:09:57.730">We are told that the circle has a
                radius of 10 centimeters.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:09:58.920" end_time="00:10:03.130">A chord of length 14 centimeters is
                drawn on the circle.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:04.740" end_time="00:10:17.740">If we let the two ends of the chord
                be points 𝐴 and 𝐵 and the center point 𝑂, then the area of the minor segment is
                equal to the area of the sector minus the area of the triangle.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:19.130" end_time="00:10:24.890">In order to calculate both of
                these, we firstly need to work out the central angle 𝜃.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:26.330" end_time="00:10:29.690">This can be done in either radians
                or degrees.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:31.050" end_time="00:10:33.460">In this question, we will use
                radians.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:33.660" end_time="00:10:37.520">So, it is important that our
                calculator is in the correct mode.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:38.860" end_time="00:10:44.710">The area of a sector, when 𝜃 is in
                radians, is equal to a half 𝑟 squared 𝜃.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:45.260" end_time="00:10:50.230">And the area of a triangle is equal
                to a half 𝑟 squared sin 𝜃.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:10:51.400" end_time="00:11:01.340">This can be simplified by
                factoring, giving us the area of the segment equal to a half 𝑟 squared multiplied
                by 𝜃 minus sin 𝜃.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:11:02.930" end_time="00:11:09.300">We can now calculate the angle 𝜃
                by using right-angle trigonometry or the cosine rule.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:10.870" end_time="00:11:17.110">In order to calculate the angle in
                any triangle using the cosine rule, we use the following formula.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:17.790" end_time="00:11:33.820">Cos of 𝐴 is equal to 𝑏 squared
                plus 𝑐 squared minus 𝑎 squared divided by two 𝑏𝑐, where 𝑎, 𝑏, and 𝑐 are the
                three lengths of the triangle and 𝐴 is the one opposite the angle we’re trying to
                work out.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:34.710" end_time="00:11:47.170">Substituting in our values gives us
                cos of 𝜃 equals 10 squared plus 10 squared minus 14 squared over two multiplied by
                10 multiplied by 10.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:48.380" end_time="00:11:52.590">This simplifies to cos of 𝜃 equals
                one fiftieth.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:11:53.950" end_time="00:12:01.810">Ensuring that our calculator is in
                radian mode, 𝜃 is equal to the inverse cos of one fiftieth.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:02.760" end_time="00:12:09.960">This is equal to 1.55079 and so on
                radians.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:12:11.350" end_time="00:12:16.910">We can now substitute this value
                into our formula for the area of a segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:18.100" end_time="00:12:25.230">The area of the minor segment is
                equal to 27.5497 and so on.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:26.550" end_time="00:12:30.140">We have been asked to calculate the
                area of the major segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:30.620" end_time="00:12:35.810">This is the area of the whole
                circle minus the area of the minor segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:36.990" end_time="00:12:40.300">The area of a circle is equal to
                𝜋𝑟 squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:41.240" end_time="00:12:47.000">As our radius is equal to 10
                centimeters, the area is equal to 100𝜋.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:48.110" end_time="00:12:54.570">We need to subtract 27.5497 and so
                on from this.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:12:55.620" end_time="00:13:01.820">This is equal to 286.6095 and so
                on.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:03.470" end_time="00:13:07.340">We’re asked to round our answer to
                the nearest square centimeter.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:08.520" end_time="00:13:11.990">The deciding number is the six in
                the tenths column.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:12.260" end_time="00:13:17.010">So, we round up to 287 square
                centimeters.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:18.020" end_time="00:13:21.510">This is the area of the major
                segment in the circle.</s>
        </p>
        </question>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:13:24.900" end_time="00:13:28.340">We will now summarize the key
                points from this video.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:30.510" end_time="00:13:37.720">A segment is a region bounded by an
                arc and a chord passing through the end points of the arc.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:38.670" end_time="00:13:46.580">Drawing a chord on any circle
                splits it into two segments, a minor segment and a major segment.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:48.150" end_time="00:13:53.810">As suggested by the name, the major
                segment is the larger of the two parts.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:13:54.940" end_time="00:14:04.640">The area of the minor segment,
                shown in orange on the diagram, is equal to the area of the pink sector minus the
                area of the blue triangle.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:05.680" end_time="00:14:14.600">In order to calculate these areas,
                we need the angle 𝜃 in either radians or degrees and the length of the radius
                𝑟.</s>
        </p>
        <p>
            <s start_time ="00:14:16.280" end_time="00:14:20.870">When dealing in degrees, we tend to
                calculate the two areas separately.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:21.360" end_time="00:14:27.890">The area of the sector is equal to
                𝜃 over 360 multiplied by 𝜋𝑟 squared.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:28.270" end_time="00:14:34.510">And the area of the triangle is
                equal to a half 𝑟 squared multiplied by sin 𝜃.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:35.470" end_time="00:14:39.290">When dealing with radians, we can
                simplify by factoring.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:39.780" end_time="00:14:48.810">The area of the segment when 𝜃 is
                in radians is a half 𝑟 squared multiplied by 𝜃 minus sin 𝜃.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:14:49.940" end_time="00:15:04.340">In any question, we can convert
                from one angle measurement to the other using the fact that 180 degrees is equal to
                𝜋 radians and, therefore, 360 degrees is equal to two 𝜋 radians.</s>
            <s start_time ="00:15:05.270" end_time="00:15:11.480">In some questions, we might need to
                use trigonometry to find out the angle 𝜃 first.</s>
        </p>
    </transcript>
</video>
