<explainer id="972198025105" country="zz" currency="none" calendar="none" unit_system="si usc" language="en"  dialect="british" publication_date="2020-10-22T10:00:00">
  <title>Measurement Tools</title>
  <seo_meta_description>In this explainer, we will learn how to identify different
    tools for the measurement of fundamental physical quantities.</seo_meta_description>
  <developer_name>Simeon Every</developer_name>
  <developer_email>simeon.every@nagwa.com</developer_email>
  <dictionary>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Anvil</from><to>Anvil</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Spindle</from><to>Spindle</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Sleeve</from><to>Sleeve</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Thimble</from><to>Thimble</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Panbalance</from><to>Pan balance</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Springbalance</from><to>Spring balance</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Slidingjaw</from><to>Sliding jaw</to></item>
    <item symbol = "false"><from>@Fixedjaw</from><to>Fixed jaw</to></item>
  </dictionary>
  <body>
    <p>In this explainer, we will learn how to identify different tools for the measurement of 
      fundamental physical quantities.</p>
    <p>Fundamental physical quantities (also called base quantities) are 
      those that cannot be obtained by combinations of other fundamental 
      quantities.</p>
      <p>The following is a list of the SI base quantities:
      <ul>
        <li>Length</li>
        <li>Time</li>
        <li>Mass</li>
        <li>Amount of substance</li>
        <li>Absolute temperature</li>
        <li>Electric current</li>
        <li>Luminous intensity</li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <p>In this explainer, we will only be considering length, time, and mass.</p>
      <p>The explainer is specifically concerned with how length, time, and mass 
        can be measured using different tools and devices.</p>
      <p>Length is measured using an instrument that is graduated with markings 
        that correspond to submultiples of a unit of length, the SI base unit 
        of which is the 
        <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>meter</unit></quantity>.</p>
      <p>A ruler is a straight-edged stick with graduated marks. An object for
        which the length is to be measured is placed along the straight edge 
        and the number of marks between the ends of the object are counted.</p> 
    <p>The marks on a ruler are usually 
      <quantity type="long"><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> 
      (<quantity ><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>) apart. 
      Usually, every <quantity><value>5</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>,
      the mark is larger to make it easier for a user to keep track of how many 
      marks have been counted. Also, an even larger mark is usually made every 
      <quantity><value>10</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>; these even
      larger marks are 
      <quantity type="long"><value>1</value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>  
      (<quantity><value>1</value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>) apart. 
      The following figure shows an enlarged section of a ruler on which the 
      marks can be seen.</p>
    <tikz src="1.tex" scale="200"> <svg src="Ruler"/></tikz>
    <p>The maximum length that can be measured by a ruler in a single measurement
      is the length of the ruler. The minimum length that can be measured by a 
      ruler is the smallest graduation of the marks on the ruler, usually 
      <quantity ><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
    <p>To measure lengths of less than 
      <quantity ><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>, different
      measuring devices are required. One such device is a vernier caliper, 
      which is shown in the following figure.</p>
    <tikz src="2.tex" scale="500"> <svg src="Two"/></tikz>
      <p>The length measured by a vernier caliper is the distance between the
        jaws of the caliper. One jaw of the caliper, called the sliding jaw, 
        can be moved away from and toward the fixed jaw so that the distance 
        between the jaws equals the length of an object. The following figure
        shows the jaws of the caliper with an object between them.</p>
    <tikz src="3.tex" scale="400"> <svg src="Three"/></tikz>
      <p>The red arrow between the jaws of the caliper is equal to the length
        of the object between the jaws. A green arrow of the same length as 
        the red arrow is shown on a graduated length of the caliper that is 
        called the main scale.</p>
      <p>The main scale of the caliper is the same as the scale of a ruler. 
        The marks are <quantity><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>
        apart and every 10 marks a 
        <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>
        mark shows the length in 
        <quantity type="long"><value></value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
      <p>Close inspection of the main scale of the caliper shown reveals that the 
        length is somewhere between 
        <quantity><value>34</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> and 
        <quantity><value>35</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>. The main 
        scale cannot measure a shorter length than this. There is, however, 
        another scale on the caliper that moves with the sliding jaw. 
        This scale is called the vernier scale.</p>
      <p>The following figure shows where the main scale and the vernier scale
        meet. The vernier scale is outlined in a dashed orange box.</p>
         <tikz src="4.tex" scale="300"> <svg src="Four"/></tikz>
      <p>The vernier scale consists of 10 marks. Each mark on the vernier scale
        is some horizontal distance from the nearest mark to it on the main 
        scale. One mark on the vernier scale has a smaller value for this 
        distance than any of the other marks. This mark is the best aligned 
        mark.</p>
      <p>The best aligned mark corresponds to a value between 0 and 9 on
        the vernier scale. This value corresponds to a length expressed in
        tenths of a 
        <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>;
        if the best aligned mark is the mark labeled 3 on the vernier scale,
        the vernier scale reads a length of 
        <latex>$<quantity><value>\frac{3}{10}</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>$</latex>.
        The vernier scale shown here can therefore measure lengths as small as one tenth of a 
        <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
      <p>Let us now look at an example in which a vernier caliper is used to measure a length.</p>
    
    <example>
      <title>Measuring a Length Using a Vernier Caliper</title>
      <question id="916168989531" instance_number="1">
        <mcq>
          <stem>
            <p>What is the length of the object being measured
              by the vernier caliper in the diagram?</p>
            <tikz src="5.tex" scale="440"> <svg src="Five"/></tikz>
           </stem>
        </mcq>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>To obtain the reading on the vernier caliper, we 
          need to record the reading on the main scale and 
          on the vernier scale.</p>
          <p>In the following figure, the main scale reading
            is shown within a dashed red box.</p>
        <tikz src="6.tex" scale="350"> <svg src="Six"/></tikz>
        <p>We can see from the main scale that there are more
          than 27 marks between the start and the end of the 
          reading, but less than 28 marks. The reading is 
          closer to 28 marks than to 27 marks. The reading 
          on the main scale is 
          <quantity><value>27</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>,
          or 
          <quantity><value>2.7</value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
          <p>In the following figure, the entire vernier 
            scale is shown within a dashed blue box.</p>
        <tikz src="7.tex" scale="290"> <svg src="Seven"/></tikz>
          <p>The vernier scale consists of the graduated 
            marks that range from 0 to 10. The reading on
            this scale corresponds to the mark for which 
            there is the least horizontal distance between
            it and the closest mark to it on the main scale.
            The appropriate mark is indicated in the following
            figure.</p>
        <tikz src="8.tex" scale="220"> <svg src="Eight"/></tikz>
          <p>This mark is the 9th on the vernier scale. Marks
            on the vernier scale correspond to lengths of a 
            tenth of a <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>, so this reading is 
            <quantity><value>0.9</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>,
            or 
            <quantity><value>0.09</value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
          <p>The full reading on the caliper, in <quantity type="long"><value></value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>, is given by
            <latex>\begin{align*}2.7 + 0.09 
              = <quantity><value>2.79</value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity>.\end{align*}</latex>
        </p>
      </answer>
    </example>
    <p>Another length-measuring device that can measure distances of less than
      <quantity><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> is an 
      instrument called a micrometer.</p>
      <p>Perhaps unhelpfully, the name of this instrument is the same as 
        the name for one-millionth of a 
        <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>meter</unit></quantity>,
        as &#x201c;micro&#x201d; means &#x201c;one-millionth.&#x201d; Less helpfully still, the 
        instrument called a micrometer cannot measure lengths as small as
        one-millionth of a 
        <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>meter</unit></quantity>!</p>
      <p>The following figure shows a micrometer and the names of its 
        most relevant parts when using it to measure a length.</p>
    <tikz src="9.tex" scale="350"> <svg src="micrometer"/></tikz>
      <p>The object that the length of is to be measured is placed
        between the anvil and the spindle. The thimble is then 
        turned until the gap between the anvil and spindle equals 
        the length of the object.</p>
      <p>When the thimble is turned, it moves along the sleeve. 
        The main scale of the 
        micrometer
        is on the sleeve. The rotating scale of the 
         micrometer
        is on the thimble. As with vernier calipers, one mark 
        on the rotating scale will most closely align to the 
        end of the main scale, and this mark will give the 
        reading of the rotating scale.</p>
      <p>Let us now look at an example in which a 
         micrometer 
        is used to measure a length.</p>
    
    <example>
      <title>Measuring a Length Using a Micrometer</title>
      <question id="958145836454" instance_number="1">
        <mcq>
          <stem>
            <p>What is the reading on the 
              micrometer
              shown in the diagram?</p>
            <tikz src="10.tex" scale="250"> <svg src="Ten"/></tikz>
          </stem>
        </mcq>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The diagram shows the main scale and rotating scale of the 
          micrometer.
          To obtain the reading on the 
           micrometer,
          we need to record the reading on the main scale and on the rotating scale.</p> 
          <p>The main scale is the horizontal line. We can see that this consists of large 
            numbered marks separated by small unnumbered marks. The large marks are 
            <quantity><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> apart and the 
            small marks are 
            <quantity><value>0.5</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> apart from
            the large marks on either side of them.</p>
          <p>We can see that the main scale reading is between 
            <quantity><value>2.5</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> and 
            <quantity><value>3</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
          <p>The rotating scale is the vertical line. It is not possible to 
            see the entire rotating scale when looking at a 
            micrometer 
            in profile, as the scale is actually a circle rather than a 
            vertical line, and half of the scale covers the unseen side
            of the thimble.</p>
          <p>The full number of marks on the rotating scale is in fact 50.
            Turning the thimble sufficiently to change the main scale 
            reading by <quantity><value>0.5</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>
            rotates the thimble through a complete revolution, leaving
            the reading on the rotating scale the same before and after
            the rotation.</p> 
          <p>The length corresponding to one mark on the rotating scale
            is given by
            <latex>\begin{align*}\frac{<quantity><value>0.5</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>}
              {50} = <quantity><value>0.01</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.\end{align*}</latex>
          </p>
          <p>This is the smallest length that a 
            micrometer 
            can measure. It is important to understand that this is not
            a length equal to 
            <quantity type="long"><value>1</value><unit>micrometer</unit></quantity>
            (<quantity><value>1</value><unit>micrometer</unit></quantity>); rather,
            it is equal to 
            <quantity><value>10</value><unit>micrometer</unit></quantity>.</p>
          <p>We can see that the mark on the rotating scale that most closely 
            aligns to the main scale is the 25th mark.</p>
          <p>The full reading on the micrometer is given by
            <latex>\begin{gather*}2.5 + <quantity><value>25 \left(0.01\right)</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>\\
              2.5 + <quantity><value>0.25</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>\\
              <quantity><value>2.75</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.\end{gather*}</latex>
          </p>
      </answer>
    </example>
    <p>Let us now look at an example involving comparing the accuracy of
      measurement tools for measuring length.</p>
    
    <example>
      <title>Comparing Tools for Measuring Length</title>
      <question id="842127405645" instance_number="1">
        <mcq>
          <stem>
            <p>Which of the following tools is the most accurate tool for measuring length?</p>
            <tikz src="11.tex" scale="250"> <svg src="Eleven"/></tikz>
            <tikz src="12.tex" scale="250"> <svg src="Twelve"/></tikz>
            <tikz src="13.tex" scale="250"> <svg src="Thirteen"/></tikz>
            <tikz src="14.tex" scale="250"> <svg src="Fourteen"/></tikz>
          </stem>
        </mcq>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The tools shown are a 
          micrometer,
          a tape measure, a ruler, and a vernier caliper.</p>
          <p>The accuracy of a measurement corresponds to how close the measured value is to the 
            real value of the quantity measured.</p>
        <p>An important difference between the tools shown is the smallest length that each can 
          measure.</p>
          <p>Consider a length measured using a ruler as shown in the following figure.</p>
        <tikz src="15.tex" scale="200"> <svg src="Fifteen"/></tikz>
        <p>The measured value of the length is 
          <quantity><value>1.1</value><unit>centimeter</unit></quantity> or 
          <quantity><value>11</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>. We can see, however,
          that the length of the object is greater than the measured length. A measuring tool
          that could measure the fraction of a 
          <quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>
          by which the length of the object exceeds 
          <quantity><value>11</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> would have a
          value closer to the length of the object. The tool that can measure the smallest 
          length is therefore the most accurate tool for measuring length.</p>
        <p>Rulers and tape measures both measure minimum lengths of 
          <quantity><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>, while vernier 
          calipers and 
          micrometer
          can measure lengths of less than 
          <quantity><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
          <p>Vernier calipers can measure a minimum length of 
            <quantity><value>0.1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>. 
            Micrometers can measure a minimum length of 
            <quantity><value>0.01</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity>.</p>
          <p>The most accurate length measuring tool is therefore a 
            micrometer.</p>
      </answer>
    </example>
    <p>Let us now look at an example that involves other measuring tools than rulers,
      vernier calipers, and 
      micrometer.</p>
    
    <example>
      <title>Identifying the Quantity Measured by Different Tools</title>
      <question id="647124934797" instance_number="1">
        <mcq>
          <stem>
            <p>Which of the following physical quantities can be measured by an hourglass,
              a pendulum clock, and a digital stopwatch?
              <ul>
                <li>Time</li>
                <li>Length</li>
                <li>Mass</li>
              </ul>
            </p>
          </stem>
        </mcq>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The terms &#x201c;clock&#x201d; and &#x201c;watch&#x201d; applied to objects are 
          familiar to most people, who would recognize that these refer to objects that give
          readings of time. The term &#x201c;hourglass&#x201d; contains the word 
          &#x201c;<quantity type="long" count="singular"><value></value>
            <unit>hour</unit></quantity>&#x201d; which is a unit of time. Time is a physical
          quantity.</p>
          <p>An object that gives a reading of time can be read at two different instances 
            to measure the time that passes between the instances.</p>
      </answer>
    </example>
    <p>Mass is an SI base quantity. Mass is often confused with the SI-derived quantity 
      &#x201c;weight.&#x201d;</p>
    <p>Measuring devices that give readings in 
      <quantity type="long"><value></value><unit>gram</unit></quantity> or 
      <quantity type="long"><value></value><unit>kilogram</unit></quantity>, and so seem
      to be measuring mass, are in fact measuring weight.</p>
      <p>Supposing that such a device was taken to the moon and used to measure the mass
        of the same object on the moon as on Earth, the result of the measurement would 
        be different, but the mass of the object would actually be the same either on 
        Earth or on the moon.</p>
      <p>Tools that measure weight can be calibrated to give readings of mass, and then
        they will correctly read the mass of an object on Earth.</p>
      <p>A tool that can measure weight is shown in the following figure. The arrow 
        shows the direction of the weight that acts.</p>
    <tikz src="16.tex" scale="100"> <svg src="Sixteen"/></tikz>
      <p>The action of the weight of a measured object extends the spring in the 
        balance. The length of the spring is used to give a reading of weight.</p>
      <p>Another such tool is shown in the following figure.</p> 
    <tikz src="17.tex" scale="300"> <svg src="Seventeen"/></tikz>
      <p>For a pan balance, two weights act, one on each pan. The pan balance 
        compares these weights. The weight on one pan is produced by an object 
        of a known mass.</p> 
      <p>Let us now look at an example involving such tools.</p>
    
    <example>
      <title>Comparing Tools for Measuring Related Quantities</title>
      <question id="259178637140" instance_number="1">
        <mcq>
          <stem>
            <p>A beam balance, a spring balance, and a digital scale are types
              of measurement tools.</p>
              <p>Which of the following physical quantities is typically measured
                by a beam balance and by a digital scale?
              <ul>
                <li>Mass</li>
                <li>Length</li>
                <li>Time</li>
                <li>Weight</li>
              </ul>
              </p>
              <p>Which of the following physical quantities is typically measured
                by a spring balance?
              <ul>
                <li>Weight</li>
                <li>Mass</li>
                <li>Length</li>
                <li>Time</li>
              </ul>
            </p>
          </stem>
        </mcq>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Balances and scales do not measure length or time, so the answer to 
          each part of the question is either mass or weight. All these tools 
          actually measure weight but can be calibrated to give readings of 
          mass or of weight.</p>
         <p>Beam balances compare the weight of an object to that of another
           object, often a standard mass. Beam balances are usually calibrated
           to read mass measurements. Digital scales are also usually calibrated
           to read mass measurements. Spring balances measure the extension of 
           a spring by an object suspended from the spring. This extension is 
           more intuitively obvious as being due to the weight of an object, 
           and spring balances are usually calibrated to read weight measurements.</p>
      </answer>
    </example>
    <p>Let us now summarize what has been learned in this explainer.</p>
    <sidebar type="definition">
      <title>Key Points</title>
      <p>
        <ol type="1">
          <li>Different tools are used to measure different physical quantities.</li> 
          <li>Lengths of less than 
            <quantity type="long"><value>1</value><unit>millimeter</unit></quantity> 
            can be measured by vernier calipers and by 
            micrometer.</li>
          <li>A tool that gives a reading of time can be read at two different instances
            to measure the time that passes between the instances.</li>
          <li>Tools for measuring mass actually measure weight but can be calibrated 
            so that if used on Earth they read the mass of objects.</li>
        </ol> 
      </p>
      </sidebar>
  </body>
</explainer>